secret garden bloomed and bloomed and every morning revealed new
miracles. In the robin's nest there were Eggs and the robin's mate sat upon them
keeping them warm with her feathery little breast and careful
wings. At first she was very nervous and the robin himself was indignantly
watchful. Even Dicken did not go near the close grown corner in those days, but
waited until by the quiet working of some mysterious spell he seemed to have
conveyed PA to the soul of the little pair that in the garden there was
nothing which was not quite like themselves— —nothing which did not
understand the wonderfulness of what was happening to them— —the immense, tender,
terrible heartbreaking beauty and solemnity of Eggs. If there had been one
person in that garden who had not known through all his or her innermost being
that if an Egg were taken away or hurt the whole world would whirl around and
crash through space and come to an end— —if there had been even one who did
not feel it and act accordingly there could have been no happiness even in
that golden springtime air. But they all knew it and felt it and
the robin and his mate knew they knew it. At first the robin watched Mary and
Colin with sharp anxiety. For some mysterious reason he knew he need not watch Dickon. The first
moment he set his duw bright black eye on Dickon he knew he was not a stranger
but a sort of robin without beak or feathers. He could speak robin (which is a
quite distinct language not to be mistaken for any other). To speak robin to
a robin is like speaking French to a Frenchman. Dickon always spoke it to the
robin himself, so the queer gibberish he used when he spoke to to humans did not
matter in the least. The robin thought he spoke this gibberish to them because
they were not intelligent enough to understand feathered speech. His movements also were
robin. They never startled one by being sudden enough to seem dangerous or
threatening. Any robin could understand Dickon, so his presence was not even
disturbing. But at the outset it seemed necessary to be on guard against the
other too In the first place the boy creature did not come into the garden on
his legs. He was pushed in on a thing with wheels and the skins of wild
animals were thrown over him. That in itself was doubtful. Then when he began to stand up
and move about he did it in a queer unaccustomed way and the others seemed
to have to help him. The robin used to secrete himself in
a bush and watch this anxiously, his head tilted first on one side and then on the
other. He thought that the slow movements might mean that he was preparing to
pounce, as cats do. When cats are preparing to pounce they creep over the ground very
slowly. The robin talked this over with his mate a great deal for a few days but
after that he decided not to speak of the subject because her terror was so
great that he was afraid it might be injurious to the
Eggs When the boy began to walk by himself and even to move more quickly it
was an immense relief. But for a long time— —or it seemed a long time to the
robin— —he was a source of some anxiety. He did not act as the other
humans did. He seemed very fond of walking but he had a way of sitting or
lying down for a while and then getting up in a disconcerting manner to begin again.
One day the robin remembered that when he himself had been made to learn to fly
by his parents he had done much the same sort of thing. He had taken short flights
of a few yards and then had been obliged to
rest. So it occurred to him that this boy was learning to fly— —or rather to
walk. He mentioned this to his mate and when he told her that the Eggs would
probably conduct themselves in the same way after they were fledged she was quite
comforted and even became eagerly interested and dered great pleasure from
watching the boy over the edge of her nest— —though she always thought that the
Eggs would be much cleverer and learn more quickly. But then she said
indulgently that humans were always more clumsy and slow than Eggs and most of
them never seemed really to learn to fly at all. You never met them in the the air
or on Treetops After a while the boy began to move about as the others did, but all
three of the children at times did unusual things. They would stand under the trees
and move their arms and legs and heads about in a way which was neither walking
nor running nor sitting down. They went through these movements at intervals
every day and the robin was never able to explain to his mate what they were
doing or trying to do. He could only say that he was sure
that the Eggs would never flap about in such a manner; but as the boy who could
speak robin so fluently was doing the thing with them, birds could be quite
sure that the actions were not of a dangerous nature. Of course neither the
robin nor his mate had ever heard of the champion wrestler, Bob harworth and his
exercises for making the muscles stand out like lumps. Robins are not like human beings;
their muscles are always exercised from the first and so they develop themselves in a natural
manner. If you have to fly about to find every meal you eat, your muscles do not
become atrophied (atrophied means wasted away through want of
use). When the boy was walking and running about and digging and weeding like the
others, the nest in the corner was brooded over by a great peace and
content. Fears for the Eggs became things of the past. Knowing that your Eggs were
as safe as if they were locked in a bank vault and the fact that you could watch
so many curious things going on made setting a most entertaining
occupation. On wet days the egg's mother sometimes felt even a little dull
because the children children did not come into the garden. But even on wet
days it could not be said that Mary and Colin were dull. One morning when the
rain streamed down unceasingly and Colin was beginning to
feel a little restive, as he was obliged to remain on his sofa because it was not
safe to get up and walk about, Mary had an inspiration. "Now that I am a real boy,"
Colin had said, "my legs and arms and all my body are so full of Magic that I
can't keep them still. They want to be doing things all the
time. Do you know that when I waken in the morning, Mary, when it's quite early
and the birds are just shouting outside and everything seems just shouting for
joy— —even the trees and things we can't really hear— —I feel as if I must jump out
of bed and shout myself. And if I did it, just think what would
happen!" Mary giggled inordinately.
"The nurse would come running and Mrs.
Medlock would come running and they would be sure you had gone crazy and
they'd send for the doctor," she said.
Colin giggled himself. He could see how they would all look— —how horrified by his outbreak and
how amazed to see him standing upright. "I wish my father would come home,"
he said. "I want to tell him myself. I'm always thinking about it— —but we couldn't
go on like this much longer. I can't stand lying still and pretending, and
besides I look too different. I wish it wasn't raining today It was then Mistress Mary had her
inspiration. "Colin," she began mysteriously, "do you know how many rooms there are in this
house?" "About a thousand, I suppose," he answered. "There's about a hundred no one
ever goes into," said Mary. "And one rainy day I went and looked into ever so many
of them. No one ever knew, though Mrs.
Medlock nearly found me out. I lost my way when I was coming back
and I stopped at the end of your corridor. That was the second time I heard you
crying Collins started up on his sofa aund rooms no one goes into," he said.
"It sounds almost like a secret garden.
Suppose we go and look at them. You could wheel me in my chair and nobody would
would know where we went." "That's what I was thinking," said
Mary. "No one would dare to follow us.
There are galleries where you could run.
We could do our exercises. There is a little Indian room
where there is a cabinet full of ivory elephants. There are all sorts of
rooms." "Ring the bell," said Colin. When the nurse came in he gave his
orders. "I want my a he said. "Miss Mary and
I are going to look at the part of the
house which is not used. John can push me as far as the picture gallery because
there are some stairs. Then he must go away and leave us alone until I send for
him again." Rainy days lost their terrors that morning. When the footman had
wheeled the chair into the picture gallery and left the two together in
obedience to orders, Colin and Mary looked at each other delighted.
As soon as Mary had made sure that Jon was really on his way back to his own
quarters below stairs, Colin got out of his chair. "I am going to run from one end of
the gallery to the other," he said, "and then I'm going to jump and then we will
do Bob Hayworth's exercises." And they did all these things and many
others. They looked at the portraits and found the plain little girl dressed in
green brickade and holding the parrot on her finger finger. "All these," said Colin, "must be my
relations. They lived a long time ago.
That parrot one, I believe, is one of my great, great, great, great aunts. She looks
rather like you, Mary— —not as you look now but as you looked when you came here. Now
you are a great deal fatter and better looking." "So are you," said Mary, and they both
laughed. They went to the Indian room and amused themselves with the ivory
elephants. They found the rose-colored brocade budoir and the hole in the
cushion the mouse had left but the mice had grown up and run away and the hole was
empty. They saw more rooms and made more discoveries than Mary had made on her first
pilgrimage They found new corridors and corners and flights of steps and new old
pictures they liked and weird old things they did not know the use of.
It was a curiously entertaining morning and the feeling of wandering
about in the same house with other people but at the same time feeling as
if one were miles away from them was a fascinating thing. "I'm glad we came," Colin said. "I
never knew I lived in such a big queer old place. I like it. We will ramble about
every rainy day. We shall always be finding new queer corners and
things." That morning they had found among other things such good appetites that
when they returned to Collin's room it was not possible to send the luncheon away
untouched. When the nurse carried the tray downstairs she slapped it down on
the kitchen dresser so that Mrs Lumis the cook, could see the highly polished
dishes and plates. "Look at that!" she said.
"This is a house of mystery, and those two children are the greatest mysteries in
it." "If they keep that up every day," said the strong young footman John, "there'd be
small wonder that he weighs twice as much today as he did a month ago. I
should have to give up my place in time, for fear of doing my muscles an injury."
That afternoon Mary noticed that something new had happened in Colin's
room. She had noticed it the day before but had said nothing because she thought
the change might have been made by chance. She said nothing today but she
sat and looked looked fixedly at the picture over the mantle She could look at it because the
curtain had been drawn aside. That was the change she
noticed. "I know what you want me to tell you," said Colin, after she had stared a
few minutes. "I always know when you want me to tell you something. You are
wondering why the curtain is drawn back.
I am going to keep it like that." "Why?" asked Mary. "Because it doesn't make me angry
anymore to see her laughing. I wakened when it was bright moonlight two nights
ago and felt as if the Magic was filling the room and making everything so
splendid that I couldn't lie still. I got up and looked out of the
window. The room was quite light and there was a patch of moonlight on the
curtain and somehow that made me go and pull the
cord. She looked right down at me as if she were laughing because she was glad I
was standing there. It made me like to look at her. I want to see her laughing
like that all the time. I think she must have been a sort of Magic person
perhaps." "You are so like her now," said Mary, "that sometimes I think perhaps you
are her ghost made into a boy." That idea seemed to impress Colin. He
thought it over and then answered her slowly. "If I were her ghost— —my father
father would be fond of me," he said. "Do you want him to be fond of you?" inquired
Mary. "I used to hate it because he was
not fond of me. If he grew fond of me I
think I should tell him about the Magic.
It might make him more
cheerful." CHAPTER